George Kimak Papers relating to Artmobile, Inc.
George Kimak Papers Relating to Artmobile, Inc.
1950-1969
Kimak, George.
3.0 linear ft.
George Kimak was an art teacher and co-founder of Artmobile, a "museum on wheels" akin to a bookmobile. Artmobile was intended to "bring original works of art to the schools of New York State" and was the shared vision of George Kimak and Barbara Chapin. Artmobile, Inc. was a non-profit corporation that oversaw the operation of the Artmobile. Collection includes correspondence and papers relating to Artmobile, Inc. and some of Kimak's personal papers, covering the years 1950 to 1969. Materials relate primarily to the planning and development of the "Artmobile concept" between 1952 and 1956.
149433
Biographical History
George Kimak was an art teacher in Baldwinsville, New York. With Barbara Chapin, he founded Artmobile, a travelling art gallery based on the same idea as library bookmobiles. Similar efforts by museums such as Illinois State Museum's Museumobile and the Trailer Museum in Cleveland had already proven successful, and the New York State Art Teachers Association was involved as a sponsor. Artmobile was intended to "bring original works of art to the schools of New York State" and in particular to make creative masterpieces physically and intellectually accessible to rural and semi-rural populations. Materials were loaned by museums, galleries, and other art institutions as well as by individuals. Artmobile, Inc. was a non-profit corporation that oversaw the operation of the Artmobile.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The George Kimak Papers Relating to Artmobile, Inc. contains correspondence and papers relating to Artmobile, Inc. and some personal papers of its co-founder George Kimak, covering the years 1950 to 1969. Materials in the collection relate primarily to the planning and development of the "Artmobile concept" between 1952 and 1956 and are divided into four series.
Official records include purpose statements, board minutes, bylaws, and membership material. Office files relate to the development and formation of the organization; letters of inquiry, solicitation and support; and promotional material. Historical files and memorabilia contains clippings, scrapbooks, and a tape of a radio program. Personal Papers of George Kimak contain biographical material, correspondence-subject files, writings, and memorabilia.
Arrangement of the Collection
Official records, office files, and historical files are arranged chronologically. Kimak's personal papers are arranged alphabetically by type.
Subject and Genre Headings
New York State; Chapin, Barbara.; Mark, Bessie.; Kimak, George.; Munzer, Bertha.; Popolizio, Vincent.; Raych, A. Morton.; Ryerson, Elbert.; Art -- Exhibitions.; Art -- Study and teaching.; Art museum directors.; Art museums -- Educational aspects.; Art museums -- New York (State); Art teachers.; Artmobile, Inc. -- Records and correspondence.; Educational exhibits, Traveling.; Educators.; Exhibitions -- New York (State); Traveling exhibitions -- New York (State); Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Memorabilia.; Photographs.; Questionnaires.; Scrapbooks.; Slides (photographs); Art museum directors.; Art teachers.; Educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Official records
  - Purpose of the Artmobile (Box 1)
  - Plan of action (Box 1)
  - Fellowship application, George Kimak - Barbara Chapin (Box 1)
  - Organizational plans - Bylaws (Box 1)
  - Board minutes - Bylaws - Progress report (Box 1)
  - Memberships and contributions (Box 1)
  - Re-chartering Artmobile, 1966 (Box 1)
- Office files
  - Development (Box 1)
    - Museums (Box 1)
    - Fund raising - foundations - industries - individuals (Box 1)
    - Funds - contributions (Box 1)
    - Promoting the Artmobile concept (Box 1)
    - Artmobile survey questionnaire (Box 1)
    - Mark, Bessie/Munzner, Bertha, Sodus, New York (Box 1)
    - Popolizio, Vincent - State Art Supervisor (Box 1)
    - Raych, A. Morton - Treasurer, New York State Art Teachers Association (Box 1)
    - Schools - educational organizations (Box 1)
    - Syracuse University, Lowe Art Center (Box 1)
    - Letters - State Education Commissioners, foundations, etc. (Box 1)
  - Formation
    - Artmobile Planning Committee meeting, Mark Twain Hotel [Elmira, NY], 1952; 2 magnetic tapes (Box 1)
    - Chapin, Barbara - Executive Secretary - Artmobile (Box 1)
    - Ryerson, Bert - Art Supervisor, Elmira Schools (Box 1)
    - Committee meetings (Box 1)
    - Plans - Correspondence between Board, Committees, etc. (Box 1)
    - Correspondence - Artmobile Committee - Board (Box 1)
    - Artmobile - reports - progress (Box 1)
    - Artmobile chairmen, New York State counties (Box 1)
    - Volunteers for Artmobile (Box 1)
    - Expenditures - prior & during Artmobile tour (Box 1)
    - Museum-on-wheels, interior design, 1954-1956 (Box 1)
    - Itinerary of pilot unit, pre-tour preparations (Box 1)
  - Letters of inquiry
    - Letters - post cards requesting information on Artmobile from various parts of the U.S.A. [untitled folder with inquiries] (Box 1)
    - Interest from abroad - Australia (Box 1)
    - Interest from abroad - Canada (Box 1)
  - Letters of solicitation
    - Art Galleries informed about Artmobile (Box 1)
    - List of individuals interested in Artmobile (Box 1)
    - Individuals informed about Artmobile project - superintendents of schools (Box 1)
    - Industries (Box 1)
    - List of organizations informed about Artmobile (Box 1)
    - Letters, individuals - organizations (Box 1)
  - Letters of support
    - Artmobile support letters (Box 2)
    - Letters of endorsement, schools - associations - museums (Box 2)
    - Photographs of endorsements (Box 2)
  - Promotion
    - Layouts - outlines for flyers and questionnaires on Artmobile (Box 2)
    - Outlines - news articles, reports, etc. (Box 2)
    - Publicity - radio/tv - newspapers - periodicals (Box 2)
- Historical files and memorabilia
  - Radio program, Corning - Station WCLI, Artmobile - [Women's Commentary Program, June Purcell], 1952; 1 magnetic tape (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clippings (scrapbook) [scrapbook material] (Box 2)
  - Articles - Museum-on-wheels, newspapers, periodicals (Box 2)
  - Articles - letters of endorsement - S.U. Cosmopolitan Club [scrapbook] (Box 2)
  - Visitors at dedication. N.Y.S. Fair [scrapbook], 1955 (Box 2)
  - Dedication of Artmobile, N.Y.S. Fair - film, 1955 (Box 2)
  - Pilot Artmobile tour, New York State [scrapbook], 1955 (Box 2)
  - Signatures, first visitors, pilot Artmobile [scrapbook], 1955 (Box 2)
  - Pilot Artmobile unit - N.Y.S. - colored slides, 26 items (Box 2)
  - New York State Artmobile (museum-on-wheels) [scrapbook] undated (Package 1)
- Personal Papers - George Kimak
  - Biographical material
    - Curriculum vitae, George Kimak [with 6 original drawings] (Box 2)
  - Correspondence-subject file (Box 2)
    - Clothes Line Art Gallery, Baldwinsville Central School (Box 2)
    - Resource Center Art Gallery, East Syracuse-Minoa Central School (Box 2)
    - Syracuse Cultural Center (Box 2)
  - Writings
    - Area XIII Educational Media Center. The State of Progress, 1968. George Kimak, Director. Council Bluffs, IA., 1969 (Box 2)
  - Memorabilia
    - Hall of Fame, New York University, 1957 (Box 2)
    - List of crafts suppliers, 1960 (Box 2)